Finding Aid for Alfred Isaac Sawyer papers, 1848-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alfred Isaac Sawyer papers 1848-1931
Sawyer, Alfred Isaac, 1828-1891.
852240 Aa 2
Homeopathic physician from Monroe, Michigan; correspondence, letterpress books, diaries, and other papers of Sawyer, his wife and daughter, and of members of the Toll family.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was the gift of Jennie Toll Sawyer (donor no. 269 ) and came to the library in 1937. The scrapbook and miscellaneous other papers came from Mrs. Florence D. Kirtland (donor no. 1963 )
The collection is open to research.
Alfred Isaac Sawyer was born in Lyme Township, Huron County, Ohio on October 31, 1828. He attended lectures at the Western College of Homeopathy in Cleveland, Ohio, receiving his degree in 1854. He formed a partnership with D. H. Beckwith of Zanesville, Ohio, then went to New York City where he attended classes in the medical department of New York University. After visiting several places, he decided to set up practice in Monroe, Michigan in 1857.
Beyond his practice, Sawyer was an advocate of homeopathy, lobbying for the recognition of homeopathy within the medical department of the University of Michigan. It took Sawyer and his supporter twenty years for the legislation to be passed and for the University to comply with it. In 1877, the University of Michigan graduated the fist class from the homeopathic department.
In addition, Sawyer was made a Mason in February 1858 and served in various capacities and writing a history of masonry in Monroe. Sawyer also was mayor of Monroe, serving 1869-70 and 1878. He died in 1891.
The Sawyer collection consists of correspondence and other papers of Alfred I. Sawyer, his wife Sarah Toll Sawyer, their daughter Jennie Toll Sawyer, and other members of the Toll family. The collection, in addition to family matters, relates to Sawyer's career as a homeopathic physician, his advocacy of the study of homeopathy within the curriculum of the University of Michigan, and his extensive activities within Masonry. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Various subjects -- Sawyer and Toll families; Homeopathy and homeopathic practice; and diaries of Sawyer and his daughter Jennie Toll Sawyer.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Freemasonry--Michigan--Monroe.; Homeopathy--Michigan.; Hotels--Michigan.; Medicine--Michigan--Monroe.; Monroe (Mich.); Physicians--Michigan--Monroe.; Railroads--Michigan.; Toledo and Northern Railroad.; Toll family.; University of Michigan. Choral Union.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Medical School.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.
Contributors:
Sawyer, Jenny Toll.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Correspondence
  - Alfred I. Sawyer
    - 1859-1863 (Box 1)
    - 1864-1873 (Box 1)
    - 1874 (Box 1)
    - 1875-1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1883 (Box 1)
    - 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - Sarah Toll Sawyer
    - Undated 1848-1851 (Box 1)
    - 1851-1852 (Box 1)
    - 1853-1856 (Box 1)
    - 1857 (Box 1)
    - 1858-1862 (Box 1)
    - 1863-1866 (Box 1)
    - 1867-1877 (Box 1)
    - 1878-1896 (Box 1)
  - Jenny T. Sawyer
    - 1872-1879 (Box 1)
    - 1880-1885 (Box 1)
    - 1887-1890 (Box 1)
    - 1908-1919 (Box 1)
  - Toll family
    - Undated 1860-1862 (Box 1)
    - 1863-1877 (Box 1)
    - 1889-1895 (Box 1)
    - 1896, 1897 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1898 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1898 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1899 (Box 1)
    - May-December 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901-1908 (Box 1)
- Various subjects -- Sawyer and Toll families
  - University of Michigan essay and notebook on Greek article (Charles Toll) circa 1855 (Box 1)
  - Toledo and Northern Railroad subscription lists and articles of incorporation (Charles Toll) 1869 (Box 1)
  - Union Hotel Association minute book and other documents (Philip Toll) 1859-1865 (Box 1)
  - Medical receipt books (Alfred Sawyer) (Box 1)
  - Legal papers (Charles Toll) (Box 1)
    (include patent for "Custer shoe" designed with George Custer, who is perhaps George A. Custer's uncle)
  - Cash book 1856-1866 (Box 1)
  - Invitations, receipts, etc. of Jennie Toll, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Manual for Masonic ceremonies (Box 1)
  - Freemasonry in Monroe, 10 folders (Box 1)
    (speeches, drafts of writings, etc.)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 7 folders (Box 1)
- Homeopathy and homeopathic practice
  - Letterpress books 1868-1878 (Box 2)
  - Letterpress books 1878-1883 (Box 3)
  - Letterpress books 1883-1891 (Box 4)
  - History of Homeopathy in Michigan, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - Homeopathy miscellaneous (speeches given before professional groups, reports on regulatory legislation, notes and drafts of writings, etc.) 1870s-1880s, undated, 17 folders (Box 5)
  - Homeopathy at the University of Michigan (scrapbook) 1875-1895 (Box 5)
- Diaries
  - Alfred I. Sawyer diaries 1857-1890, 36 volumes (Box 6)
  - Jenny Toll Sawyer diaries 1881-1931, 21 volumes (Box 6)